Guide to the Mark Danner Papers, 1970-2004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mark Danner papers 1985-2004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Danner, Mark.
6.0 linear feet Extent: 4500 Items
Mark Danner is a writer, journalist, and professor at the University of California at Berkeley. His work covers politics and foreign affairs, with a focus on war and conflict. The Mark Danner Papers date from 1970 to 2004 and focus predominately on Danner's coverage of Haiti during the period of unrest that followed President Jean-Claude ("Baby Doc") Duvalier's exile in 1986. Additional materials document Danner's interest in the Balkan Wars during the 1990's and preliminary research on the El Mozote massacre in El Salvador. These materials include research notes, travel information, newspaper clippings, and VHS tapes.
RL.00304
Language: Material in English, French
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. However, original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.
Electronic records have been migrated to a library server. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Also, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. Consequently, there may be a 24-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Mark Danner Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2013.
Biographical Note
Mark Danner is a writer, journalist, and professor at the University of California at Berkeley. His work covers politics and foreign affairs, with a focus on war and conflict.
Collection Overview
The Mark Danner Papers document Danner's career as a prominent writer and journalist. Materials in the collection date from 1970 to 2004, and primarily document Danner's work on Haiti during the years following Jean-Claude Duvalier's exile in 1986 and the rise of Jean-Bertrand Aristide in the 1990's. The notes, correspondence, travel information, and newspaper clippings constitute part of Danner's research during his work for The New Yorker, The New York Times Magazine, and the New York Review of Books.
The Newspaper Clippings series contains newspaper clippings from various newspapers and newsletters concerning the turmoil in Haiti.
The Government Documents series includes documentation of U.S. government institutions' views and actions towards Haiti, as well as documents from the Haitian government, including a copy of the 1987 constitution.
The T.V. and Radio Transcripts series comprises interviews conducted with various U.S. and Haitian officials and citizens for media outlets such as ABC News.
The Printed Materials series contains a variety of documents from human rights organizations such as Amnesty International and news organizations such as the Foreign Broadcast International Service cables, in addition to flyers and other materials from Haiti. A selection of Danner's own articles on Haiti are also included.
The Research Materials series comprises materials Danner collected on Haiti (notably, records of the U.S. District Court Front Pour l'Avancement et le Progres Haitien -FRAPH court case) as well as documents for other subjects, such as the Balkans, El Mozote, and the World Bank.
The Personal series includes documentation of Danner's travels along with notes and correspondence.
The Tapes series contains VHS tapes which Danner collected as part of his research on Haiti.
The collection also includes two 3.5" floppy disks with files created by Danner. These have been migrated to the Electronic Records server for preservation and are available by contacting Research Services in advance.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Danner, Mark, 1958-; Duvalier, Jean-Claude, 1951-; Dictatorship -- Latin America -- History -- 20th century; Haiti -- History -- 20th century; Haiti -- Politics and government -- 20th century; United States -- Foreign relations -- Haiti
Contents of Collection
- Newspaper Clippings, 1970-2004, (2 boxes)
  This series contains clippings from various newspapers and newsletters with articles pertaining to Haiti. These materials are organized chronologically, with separate folders for the Haiti Hebdo, a weekly news publication.
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1970s (Box 1)
  - 1985 (Box 1)
  - 1986 (Box 1)
  - 1987 (Box 1)
  - 1988 (Box 1)
  - 1989 (Box 1)
  - 1990 (Box 1)
  - 1991 (Box 1)
  - 1992 (Box 1)
  - 1993, (2 folders) (Box 1-2)
  - 1994, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1995 (Box 2)
  - 1996 (Box 2)
  - 1999 (Box 2)
  - 2003-2004 (Box 2)
  - Haiti Hebdo, (2 folders) (Box 3)
- Government Documents, 1985-1995, (Less than 1 box)
  The Government Documents series is divided into two subseries. The first, U.S. Government Documents, contains materials from the U.S. State Department, Department of Defense, etc. that are related to Haiti and which Danner collected as part of his research on the island. The second subseries, Haiti Government Documents, includes pamphlets, speeches, and flyers issued by the Haitian government. Most of this material comes from the late 1980s and early 1990s, and includes a printed copy of the 1987 version of Haiti's constitution.
  - Central Intelligence Agency (Box 3)
  - U.S. Senate Committee on Foreign Affairs (Box 3)
  - Department of Defense Information Reports (Box 3)
  - U.S. State Department, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - U.N. Reports (Box 3)
  - Haiti Government Papers, 1987-1995 (Box 3)
- T.V. and Radio Transcripts, 1987-1995, (1 box)
  This series includes printed transcripts of interviews with various individuals including Haiti citizens, politicians, journalists, etc. The majority of these transcripts are printed on letterhead indicating the media outlet for which they were intended (i.e. ABC News) and, occasionally, the newscaster who was to present the material. The transcripts are organized by date, with the exception of materials Danner kept separately in large binders. These are organized by the binder label, which is also the name of the newsdesk for whom the interviews were conducted (i.e. ABC -Washington Interviews). Within these folders, the transcripts are organized by the name of the interview subject.
  - 1991-1993 (Box 3)
  - 1994, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Undated (Box 3)
  - ABC Washington Interviews, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - ABC NY and Miami Interviews, (2 folders) (Box 3-4)
  - ABC Haiti Interviews, (2 folders) (Box 4)
- Printed Materials, 1987-2004, (2 boxes)
  The Printed Materials series encompasses a large variety of documents, including reports by human rights organizations such as Amnesty International, newsletters, foreign affairs papers, and magazines and journals in both French and English which Danner collected for his research on Haiti. A selection of Danner's own articles about Haiti are also included.
  Many of the documents are papers and reports on the changing political and economic situation in Haiti in the early 1990s. The Foreign Broadcast International Service Cables are daily news briefings for the Caribbean region. In addition to more formal printed documents, the series contains printed flyers from Haiti, some of which present political candidates. The materials in this series are organized by format.
  - Foreign Broadcast International Service Cables (Box 4)
  - Human Rights Reports, (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Washington Office on Haiti (Box 4)
  - Newsletters, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Foreign Affairs Papers (Box 4)
  - Reports and Papers, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Magazines and Journals (English), (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Magazines and Journals (French) (Box 5)
  - Danner Articles on Haiti (Box 5)
- Research Materials, 1987-2004, (Less than 1 box)
  The Research Materials series includes materials Danner collected on Haiti (notably, records of the U.S. District Court Front Pour l'Avancement et le Progres Haitien (FRAPH) court case). These materials are organized by format, with the exception of materials Danner had organized in research binders: these documents are kept together in separate folders.
  In addition to the materials which discuss Haiti, the Research Materials series includes information which Danner collected on other contemporary news issues, including wars in the Balkans and El Salvador, among others.
  - U.S. District court FRAPH Case, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Presidential Business Development Mission to Haiti Binder (1995) (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Haiti Research Binder, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - World Bank (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Cultural Events, Films, etc. (Box 5)
  - Balkan Wars (Box 5)
  - Chile (Box 5)
  - Asia (Box 5)
  - El Salvador (Box 5)
  - Transatlantic Relations (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Subjects (Box 5)
- Personal, 1987-2004, (Less than 1 box)
  The brief Personal subseries contains information on Danner, much of which is related to his Haiti work. These documents include flyers and agendas for events Danner attended, notes, correspondence, and travel information for Danner's trips to Haiti.
  - Travel (Box 5)
  - Events (Box 5)
  - Notes (Box 5)
  - Correspondence (Box 5)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1987-2004, (1 box)
  The Audiovisual series includes VHS recordings of various programs on which Danner either worked or collected for research purposes. The tapes are listed by the information on their label.
  [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
  - J. B. Aristide Campagne Presidentielle (1990) (Box 6)
  - Haiti Dreams of Democracy (Box 6)
  - MTV (3-15-93) (Box 6)
  - Prestation (Box 6)
  - Joi Fabrius (11/91) (Box 6)
  - Fort Dimanche (Box 6)
  - President Jean Bertrand Aristide Explains the Coup (Box 6)
  - LaFontant Trial, Part 1 (Box 6)
  - LaFontant Trial, Part 2 (Box 6)
  - LaFontant Coup (Box 6)
  - Frontline: Showdown in Haiti (PBS Airdate: June 14, 1994) (Box 6)
  - Aristide with the Poor (Box 6)
  - Aristide Speech about the Fire (Box 6)